and today I bring you five new CSS rules
functions and pseudo classes that you
didn't know existed my favorite one
makes CSS feel a bit more like a
programming language so make sure to
watch the video Until the End to know
which one it is support is an ad rule
it's called at rule because you first
write the ad symbol and then the name of
the rule the ad support rule allows you
to write conditional CSS code that will
run only if the browser supports a
feature or not it is very easy to use
all we have to do is write add supports
followed by the property we want to test
for followed by our conditional code
when using the add support rule it is
better to provide fallbacks or default
value like here where you can see how
the header of our page is by default a
display flex but on a browsers that
supports CSS grid the header will be a
display great if we write our code like
this we can be sure that our website
does not look broken on browsers that
don't support some features and on
browsers that do our website can look
even better we can also use the add
support rule with the not operator which
negates the expression like here where
we are showing an alert to the user if
the browser does not support border
radius you could also chain multiples
knots together to negate the negation if
you wanted to apart from the not
operator we also have and and or and we
can combine them if we want to the and
the operator checks if all the
conditions are true like here where we
are checking if the browser supports
display flex and display grid and if
that is not true we are showing an alert
to the user the or operator in contrast
will evaluate to true if one of the
conditions is true like here where we
are checking if Scrolls now type is
supported with the Microsoft prefix or
not apart from testing for CSS
properties we can also test for the
support of a selector using the selector
function like on this code where we are
using the selector function to test if
the browser supports the first child
selector add supports rule along with
the selector function are supported by
all major browsers today being able to
test for properties and selectors is
very useful if you combine it with the
next item in our list 8th child is a
pseudo class that isn't new at all I am
sure you've heard of it it allows you to
select for example the fourth item on a
list the even items on a list the old
items on a list or all the fifth items
on a list like 5 10 15 and 20. what is
new about this sudo class is the off
selector syntax and it looks like this
on this code out of all the children
that have the link class we are
selecting the number three which is very
different from doing something like this
what this code is doing is selecting the
item number three that also has a class
link which is different from what we
want for example with this HTML and CSS
the second list item will be selected
since it is the item number two and it
also has the link class but with this
CSS using the new off selector syntax
the fifth least item will be selected
since out of all the items with the
class link it is the second one you can
also use comma to include other
selectors as wet the nth child of
selector syntax is supported on all
major browsers apart from Firefox that
has a block currently being worked on
the next item in our list is the is sudo
class function it helps us write shorter
and more compact code take this code for
example here we have a title that is 18
pixels if I wanted to change the size of
the title only when it's inside of a
section on an article or a leaf my code
would look something like this now if I
wanted to change the size of the title
also when it's inside of a section an
article or a div that is inside of a
section an article or a div my code
would look something like this that does
not look good this was the problem that
is pseudo class function was created to
solve accomplishing the same goal but
using the is pseudo class function our
code looks like this there is sudo class
function will take a list of selectors
and select any of the elements that can
be selected by any of the selectors on
that list so in the first case it will
select the H1 that is inside of a
section or an article or a div and just
like on the second case we can use the
ace pseudo class functions next to each
other to get a title that may be inside
of a section an article or a div that in
turn is inside of a section an article
or a div if you compare the code before
and after there is no question about
what's best there is sudo class function
is supported in all major browsers the
next item in our list is my favorite is
another ad rule called property it is
fairly experimental but it supercharges
CSS of variables and makes them more
powerful it is part of the CSS Houdini
project which is a group of low-level
apis that allow us developers to have
much more direct contact with the
browser's rendering engine when we use
CSS variables we do something like this
where we first create the variable and
then we use it this is fine but how cool
would it be if we made the variables
smarter by giving them a default values
to be able to override them and even
type to do that we use the add property
Rule and name our property primary color
then we tell the browser that the type
of value that this property will hold is
a color and then we give it an initial
value of red last but not least we can
choose if this property can be inherited
if we set that to true this property
will inherit the value from its father
and if it's false it won't then when
it's time to use our newly declared
property we use it as a normal CSS
variable and if we want to change the
color of our link when the mouse is over
it all we have to do is set the value of
primary color to something else the
interesting thing happens at the end of
our code there we are setting primary
color to false which isn't a color but
what this will do because we are using
the add property rule is to set the
value of primary color back to its
initial value which in our case is red
the add property rule supports other
kinds of syntax as well it can hold
percentages URLs transform functions and
many more it's not a hundred percent
supported but it's getting there and
talking about the support the last item
in our list is a super sweet CSS
function called the image function that
is not supported anywhere at all no
support zero but I wish it was when we
add an image as a background on CSS we
do something like this this loads the
whole image and we can customize its
size or if it stretches if it covers the
whole page Etc what we cannot do is crop
the image this is what the CSS image
function will do one day with the image
function it will be possible to do
something like this here we are loading
the photo of our Dock and we are drawing
a photo that starts on zero on the X and
Y axis which is the top left corner of
our image we are making the Box a
hundred pixels wide and 200 pixels store
after that the rest of the image will be
big crop in only the region inside of
our box will be the background image of
our body I really can't wait for this to
arrive in all browsers I hope it happens
soon but I would not get my hopes High
since the specification was defined more
than 12 years ago now it's your turn let
me know in the comments two things
number one which one of all these new
features is your favorite and number two
which one if any did you all already
know and don't forget that if you want
to learn JavaScript python react react
native gold dark flutter among many many
others for absolutely free all you have
to do is click the link below to join
any of our many free courses that you
can take right now for absolutely free
with me click the link below and I will
see you there I hope you find the video
useful
see you on the next one bye